<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The reformation of the church to be endeavoured more then that of the common-vvealth, declared, in a sermon preached before the Right Honourable House of Lords at the publike fast, August 27. 1645. / By Anthony Burges, pastour of Sutton Coldfield, and now preacher at Laurence-Jury, London.</title>
            <author>Burgess, Anthony, d. 1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77847</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5654</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E298_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200236</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861042</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861042</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113169</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77847)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113169)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 49:E298[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The reformation of the church to be endeavoured more then that of the common-vvealth, declared, in a sermon preached before the Right Honourable House of Lords at the publike fast, August 27. 1645. / By Anthony Burges, pastour of Sutton Coldfield, and now preacher at Laurence-Jury, London.</title>
                  <author>Burgess, Anthony, d. 1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by G.M. for T. Vnderhill at the Bible in Woodstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Judges VI, 27-29 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113169:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE REFORMATION OF THE CHURCH To be endeavoured more then that of the COMMON-VVEALTH,</p>
            <p>Declared, In a Sermon preached before the Right Honourable Houſe of LORDS at the publike Faſt, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 27. 1645.</p>
            <p>By ANTHONY BURGES, Paſtour of <hi>Sutton Coldfield,</hi> and now Preacher at <hi>Laurence</hi>-Jury, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G.M.</hi> for <hi>T. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderhill</hi> at the Bible in Woodſtreet, 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:113169:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die Iovis <hi>28.</hi> Auguſt. <hi>1645.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is this day ordered by the Lords in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled, That M. <hi>Anthony Burgeſse,</hi> who preached yeſterday before their Lordſhips in the Abbey Church, <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> it being the day of the publike Faſt, is hereby thanked for his great pains he took in his ſaid Sermon, and deſired to print and publiſh the ſame, which is only to be done by authority under his hand.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohn Brown, <hi>Cleric. Parliamentorum.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>I Appoint <hi>Thomas Vnderhill</hi> to print this Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Anthony Burgeſs.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113169:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE Houſe of PEERS Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONOURABLE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Scripture taketh notice of thoſe,
<note place="margin">Act. 17.11.</note> as more noble then others, that enquire and ſearch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently into the Scripture, concerning the truth of things tendered to be believed. And well doth it honour ſuch, becauſe men are apt in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion (as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeaketh about the opinions of an happy life) <hi>Credere magis quàm judicare,</hi> believe implicite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rather then judge exactly, whereby they walk, <hi>Non quâ eundum eſt, ſed quâ itur,</hi> not whither we ſhould goe, but whither the tract of the path leadeth us. It was my endeavour in this Sermon to excite your Lordſhips to a ſpeedy and exact Reformation of the Church from all the corruptions that have defiled her, and herein to attend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods Word, as the only ſtarre that will conduct unto Chriſt. None are too great to undertake ſo good a work. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaid of <hi>David</hi> dancing before the Ark, <hi>Magis miror</hi> Davidem <hi>ſaltantem, quàm pugnantem, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:113169:3"/>is more to be admired in his religious worſhip of God, then in his couragious conqueſts and ſlaughters of the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims,</hi> or other enemies. Hence, <hi>Jer. 9.23, 24.</hi> where glory in wiſdome, riches and might is forbidden, there is a kinde of an holy pride allowed in the knowledge of the Lord. Let Heathens glory that they are ſaluted by the Common-wealth, <hi>patres patriae;</hi> but let thoſe Chriſtians, whom God honoureth with dignity and place, delight to be nurſing Fathers unto the Church, by ſpeaking comfortably unto thoſe who teach the good knowledge of God; and by commanding the Levites to carry all the filthineſse out of the Temple. Which that your Lordſhips may faithfully and zealouſly doe, is the prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips humble Servant <hi>Anthony Burgeſse.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 4. line 21. for <hi>counſelled</hi> read <hi>compelled.</hi> againſt l. 29. adde <hi>Calv. in Amos, ch.</hi> 7 <hi>v.</hi> 13. p. 15. l 9. for <hi>ſubtitis</hi> r. <hi>ſubditis.</hi> p. 26. l. 8. for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> p. <hi>ult.</hi> l. 28. reade, <hi>but left the ſaithfull Miniſters and godly people of the land, under as many groanes and troubles as before.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113169:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Houſe of LORDS, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 28, 1645.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>JUDG. 6.27, 28, 29.</bibl>
                  <p>Then Gideon took ten men of his ſervants, and did as the Lord had ſaid unto him: And ſo it was, becauſe he feared his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſhold, and the men of the City, that he would not do it by day, that he did it by night.</p>
                  <p>And wen the men of the City roſe early in the morning, behold, the altar of Baal was caſt down, and the grove was cut down that was by it, and the ſecond bullock was offered upon the altar that was built.</p>
                  <p>And they ſaid one to another, Who hath done this thing? And when they enquired and asked, they ſaid, Gideon the ſonne of Joaſh hath done this thing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His book containeth a wonderfull alterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and viciſſitude of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and their deliverances, as alſo of their ſinnes, and prayers unto God; which old inconſtancie of theirs, made <hi>Gregory</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them to the graſhoppers, that do on a ſodaine leape high, and then fall down again to the ground: Thus did the <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> and this Chapter containeth the fourth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113169:4"/>change, wherein we have firſt deſcribed their ſinne, and then their puniſhment; Their ſinne, <hi>ver.</hi> 1. <hi>(The children of Iſrael did evil in the ſight of the Lord:)</hi> This evil was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially Idolatry; hence that is called in Scripture <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the abominable thing; and this Idolatry is either when the true God is not worſhipped, or when he is not worſhipped in a true manner. It is not long ſince in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> were found ſuch abominable things, which made the faithfull Miniſters of God, ſo zealous for a Reformation; <hi>Omnis ſermo adaptandus eſt contra Idolatriam.</hi> In the next place, you have their puniſhment, they were oppreſſed by the <hi>Midianites:</hi> and this was ſo great, that the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who had been beaſts in their ſinnes, were now made like them in their puniſhments; for they were forced to hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in dens and caves; and this was not all, they were in danger of ſcarcity and famine; for they found it very difficult to get corne; now the words that do expreſſe the miſery of warre, as <hi>clades, ſtrages</hi> and <hi>calamitas,</hi> are ſuch as are taken from the hurt done to the husbandman, in his corne and graſſe, as if that were the great evil of warre.</p>
            <p>In the next place we have <hi>Iſraels</hi> prayer unto God, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. <hi>They cried unto the Lord.</hi> At <hi>ver.</hi> 7. God ſendeth a Prophet to them, to informe them of their ſinne, that the weight thereof might lye heavier upon them, then all outward miſery; which alſo is aggravated by the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold favours God hath beſtowed on them: now it is ind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by ſome, that here is an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the hiſtory, and that this expoſtulation, which the Prophet made with them, did precede and cauſe the prayers and ſupplications of the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> What the Prophet was, and whether it was the ſame with the Angel mentioned, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. I will not diſcuſſe. Upon the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> humiliation, God ſends
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113169:4"/>them a deliverer, who is deſcribed by his name, <hi>family,</hi> and his preſent action <hi>(he was threſhing wheat:)</hi> A fit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of him who was afterwards in the worſhip of God, to ſeparate the wheat and the chaffe. In the Chapter we have, 1. His call and commiſſion; 2. His humble and modeſt excuſe, 3. His obedience notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: Now his commiſſion was in two things prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally; Firſt, The deſtruction of all falſe worſhip, with erecting and eſtabliſhing of the pure: And ſecondly, The vindicating and aſſerting of the Common wealth from its oppreſſors: And my text containeth <hi>Gideons</hi> faithfull diſcharge of the former part of his commiſſion, though he met with much oppoſition. Now in this whole fact of <hi>Gideons,</hi> ſome things are extraordinary, and do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long as examples to us; but other things are ordinary, and from thoſe I ſhall gather my preſent obſervations: As firſt, whereas <hi>Gideon</hi> doth not only free the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth from outward violence and oppreſſion, but the Church alſo from corrupt worſhip and Idolatry; we may conclude;</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>That it is an happy thing, when thoſe Magiſtrates, whom God raiſeth up to aſſert the freedoms of a Common wealth, do alſo endeavour a reformation of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond place; whereas you ſee <hi>Gideon</hi> much op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and that by the multitude of people, and the deareſt of his friends, in ſo much that had he not been endowed with extraordinary piety and magnanimity from above, he could never have performed this great ſervice to God; we may obſerve;</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>That there is a neceſsity of the concurrence of many ſpeciall abilities and graces in thoſe who undertake a Reformation.</hi> I will begin with the firſt Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Before we lay down the grounds of this, take notice,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113169:5"/>that it lyeth as a duty upon Magiſtrates, to attend to the reformation of all corruptions that creep into the Church, as well as to redreſſe the abuſes in a ſtate: Only concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his power herein, there is a two-fold extremity by way of errour; firſt, of Popery, who do not well approve, that the Magiſtrate ſhould meddle in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; but would have him altogether bound up in the determinations of the Pope and his Biſhops; and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially they abhorre this doctrine, when it extendeth to the reformation of the Eccleſiaſticall perſons; But we ſee in the Scripture, the godly Magiſtrates, <hi>Hezekiah, Joſiah</hi> and others, demoliſhing the Altars, incouraging the Prieſts that taught the good knowledge of God, and puniſhing Baals Prieſts; and where theſe things have not been done, there we finde the Magiſtrates reproved: on the other ſide, the errour may be extreme, when we give them an unlimited power in eſtabliſhing matters of Religion; as if they were not to be regulated by Scripture, or to take the advice and counſell of thoſe that are Spirituall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours in the Church: Thus <hi>Constantius</hi> is branded, who when he would have counſelled the Orthodox to Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, he uttered that ſpeech full of pride, <hi>quod ego volo, pro canone ſit;</hi> what I will, ſhall ſtand for a rule: Thus al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo we go too farre, when we confound Civill power and Eccleſiaſtique, making the former wholly to devoure the latter: Hence <hi>Calvin</hi> ſpeaking of the duty of Kings and all in authority, to uſe the ſword for the defence of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and the worſhip of God; yet addeth, that there are <hi>inconſiderati homines,</hi> &amp;c. ſome raſh and indiſcreet men, who go beyond their bounds in ſetting up the Magiſtrates power, ſo that they do <hi>abolere omne ſpirituale regimen,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh all ſpirituall government. By this briefly it may be ſeen, that it is the Migiſtrates duty, to eſtabliſh the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113169:5"/>worſhip of God, to reforme corruptions in the Church; yet with ſome rules and grounds. I come therefore to the reaſons, why Governours ought to lay to heart, and to be affected with Church matters, as well as thoſe of the ſtate.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>As 1. Becauſe Gods bleſſing doth moſt remarkably follow their other enterpriſes; Hence <hi>Hag.</hi> 1. God bids them conſider, whether they did not thrive accordingly as they promoted the building of the Temple; and thus <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> when he beſtirred himſelfe in a reformation, fear fell upon all the nations round about, that they dared not to warre with him; and on the contrary, how was <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> and <hi>Rehoboams</hi> kingdome ſhaken, when they corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted the worſhip of God? If we would judge by Scripture, we ſhould ſee horrible wickedneſſe and impiety in thoſe ſpeeches of men, which ſay; It is this ſtrictneſſe, this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation that brings all our calamities upon us: men that will not be perſwaded, their own oaths, drunkenneſſe and ungodly practices do make the land miſerable, will yet thinke the prayers and active endeavours of the godly to bring all our ruine upon us. 1. This is no Scripture judgement. If therefore we would have God ſubdue our enemies, and thoſe that hate us, let Magiſtrates ſubdue that which is an enemy to God, corrupt worſhip, defiled adminiſtrations of ordinances, theſe are enemies to God. It is true, ſometimes God, to try the conſtancie of reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and their faithfullneſſe, hath brought much warre and calamity upon them, preſently upon finiſhing the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, as 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Herein are concerned the ſouls of men: certainly this ought much to inflame, and kindle your affections in a Church-reformation, that hereby you may preſerve the ſouls of thouſands from everlaſting perdition. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolies
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113169:6"/>and illegall taxes, theſe onely waſte the outward eſtates of men; but corrupt worſhip, doth the ſouls of men. You doe bemoan thoſe thouſands that have loſt their blood in the field, ſince the warrs began; but (had not God ſtirred up Governours to reform) how many thouſands of ſouls would have periſhed through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and ſuperſtition? So that <hi>Joſeph</hi> was never in more mercy raiſed up by God to preſerve his Father and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren from famine in time of dearth, then when God moved the hearts of divers in eminent places, to cauſe the plenty of Gods Word. Know therefore (Right Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able) that by your places and power, which God hath committed to you, you may ſave the ſouls of many. Look upon it, as the leaſt thing, that the people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> may by your means have their bodies and eſtates ſecurely provided for; but account it the greateſt obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and tie upon you, to provide for their ſouls and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall happineſſe. There are ſpirituall plunderings as well as corporall; and there is the ſiring of ſouls as well as houſes and towns: therefore let your thoughts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations be to prevent theſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The devil uſeth all his malice and power for the ſubverting of this rather then the other. Wherein doth the devils great enmity and rage appear againſt men? It is not againſt their purſes, their bodies, their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward comforts, ſo much as againſt their ſouls.</p>
               <p>The devil and his inſtruments they chiefly labour, that there may be no pure doctrine, no holy diſcipline, no godlineſſe promoted; to ſtop this, all the power of hell combine: ſo that the greateſt, and the moſt dangerous part of our warre at this time is with the powers of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which ſtirre up inſtruments to promote that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of darkneſſe.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113169:6"/>
               <p>As they report of the Baſilisk, it hateth man ſo much, that whereſoever it ſeeth the image or picture of him, it endeavours to tear it in peeces; ſuch is the hatred of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan and his inſtruments to any thing of God, appearing in doctrine, worſhip, or diſcipline, that he would pull all into pieces; and certainly the confuſions that the devil hath brought upon Churches by hereſies and impieties, are more dreadfull and terrible then all the devaſtations and deſolations he hath brought upon States and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, by the ſword or other calamities. Let this therefore awaken men in place and authority; and let them thinke, what is that which hell, which the devils, which wicked men would ſo gladly have, and they ſhall ſee it is nothing, but a diſſolute, careleſſe, and impenitent life, without any check from the Word of God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Gods care about his Church is farre above that to the Common-wealth. Therefore learn from God, let your affections and thoughts be moſt about that, which God hath the greateſt care about from all eternity.</p>
               <p>He looks to the Common-wealth in the way of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as a God abſolutely conſidered; but to his Church, in the decree of Election, and acts of Juſtification and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, as a gracious Father; therefore God, he doth ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bleſſe, or afflict Common-wealths, and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours thereof, as they are either froward and churliſh, or kinde and mercifull to his people, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87.2. <hi>Jehovah lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the gates of Sion more then the dwelling places of Jacob;</hi> the place of his worſhip and ordinances, more then all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places. Thinke therefore, that if Gods love, and works in a remarkable manner be for his people, worſhip and ordinances, how effectuall and ſtrong ought the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions and endeavours of thoſe be, who by reaſon of their place and office are called gods? and if it was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113169:7"/>ſuch an honour among the Heathens unto <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> that he cleanſed their <hi>Augean</hi> ſtable, and conquered their many-headed <hi>Hydra;</hi> how much more will it be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of honour and glory, to cleanſe the temple of God from all defilements, and to ſubdue all hereſies, that riſe up againſt the truths of Chriſt? let us therefore all imitate God, in our places and relations, by our love and thoughts of good to the Church and ordinances of God.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Common-wealth is in reference and ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to that: the Church is not for the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, but the Common-wealth for the Church. Hence a Common-wealth is made glorious, when it becometh holy and Chriſtian, as jewels, which they ſay have their being at firſt in the ſea, yet have more affinity with the heavens, whoſe colour they repreſent; ſo a State when once become the Church of God, doth more depend on heaven, from whence it hath it's originall, then on the earth, in which it liveth. And then doe all Governours contradict this principle, when they make the Scripture ſubordinate to State-ends or policies: Thus <hi>Jeroboam</hi> makes the worſhip of God ſubordinate to the outward peace of the Kingdom; and this hath been the fatall miſcarriage of many Governours; they have not conſulted what God and his Word ſpeaketh, but what are the maximes and principles of State. If therefore your hearts and affections be for the Common-wealth, how much more ought it be for the Church, ſeeing God made the world at firſt, and doth ſtill preſerve it, becauſe of his Church that is in it? and if Chriſt thought not his own bloud too much to give for the ranſome of it, how much leſſe ſhould we judge our pains and thoughts too much for it? <hi>Pſal</hi> 2. There is a forcible exhortation to all the governours of the earth, to receive Chriſt, and to ſubmit to his govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113169:7"/>let none thinke himſelfe too great to be in Chriſts yoke; nay, this is the end why God hath given greatneſſe and power to men, that they might ſerve his Church; and therefore he ſuffers her to be in a weake and indigent eſtate: when the Lord promiſeth, that Kings and Queens ſhall be nurſing fathers, and nurſing mothers, it ſuppoſeth the Church to be like a poor helpleſſe orphan: now when we ſpeak thus of helping the Church of God, we mean not in ſuch a manner, as they in Popery plead for the outward dignity and carnall priviledges, as alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull authority, which are not of Chriſts kingdom; but we ſpeak of the people of God, the Ordinances, the true Doctrine, and the wholeſome diſcipline thereof; we deſire this to be eſtabliſhed and promoted by you. Who ſeeth not a vaſt difference between the ſpirit of a proud <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi> obſtinately dying for the outward pompe and uſurped power of the Church (as they call it) and the zeal of a <hi>Calvin,</hi> chooſing puniſhment, yea (a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred deaths) as he ſaith, rather then to ſuffer the publike prophanation of the Lords Supper. <hi>Plato</hi> ſaid, <hi>magis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandam eſſe patriam quàm matrem, quia patria quiddam di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinum eſt:</hi> how much rather then are we to love the Church of God, above the Common wealth, becauſe that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed divine, being the immediate plant of Chriſt himſelf?</p>
               <p n="6">6. God in laying down a law, doth command thoſe things firſt, that concerne him and his worſhip; ſo his promiſes to his Church, are chiefly about the ſpirituall means of ſalvation; this conſideration may alſo be a great motive in the worke of reformation. God in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, firſt doth eſtabliſh the duties of worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to him, and then the offices and duties towards man; how happy then is it, when men make laws proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to God?</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:113169:8"/>
               <p>Thus <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Varro. <hi>l.</hi> 14 <hi>c.</hi> 17. <hi>Romae quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſcun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus cogeratur nullâ de re pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, quam de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligione ageba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi>
                  </note> as ſoon as he had delivered the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> before they were a ſetled Common wealth, he preſcribeth them all the forme and manner of Gods worſhip; and here <hi>Gideon</hi> in the text, before he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dueth the <hi>Midianites,</hi> he deſtroyeth their Idols. And as you have Gods commands, ſo alſo his promiſes to his Church are chiefly in reſpect of ſpirituall things, <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.6, 7. One would not have thought that the glory there propheſied of for the Temple, ſhould have been the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation that Chriſt did bring into it, but rather would have expected ſome outward materiall magnificence: Even as in Popery, adorned Temples, goodly Images, and coſtly veſtments, are accounted the glory of a Church: but we ſee the promiſe is otherwiſe: So <hi>Zach.</hi> 12. and <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. the promiſes of God to his people under the Goſpel, are not that they ſhall live free from taxes and pillaging, but that they ſhall have a refining Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, pure Ordinances, and gracious affections in the uſe of them.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The oppreſſions in worſhip and Religion are farre more grievous then thoſe of the outward man; therefore ought Magiſtrates to eaſe the godly in theſe reſpects, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then in any other. No doubt to the godly <hi>Iſraelites, Gideon</hi> was more welcome, in that he deſtroyed Altars, then in that he vanquiſhed the <hi>Midianites.</hi> Conſcience is the eye of a man, and any little crumme of duſt blown into that is very grievous; This made our godly ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, lying under the burdens of Popery, to cry out, like <hi>David,</hi> for the water of <hi>Bethlehem;</hi> Who will give us to drinke of the pure waters of Gods ordinances? How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have found an hell in their hearts, for communicating with falſe worſhip? Our worthy reformers at firſt, if it had been matter of purſe or ſtate, they could have born
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113169:8"/>it; but when oppreſſions were in doctrine and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, this made them chooſe reproaches with Chriſt, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the treaſures of <hi>Rome.</hi> It is true, there are men whoſe conſciences are like the Leviathans skinne, no ſpear can enter into them; let there be an Image ſet in the room of <hi>David,</hi> any Idols in the place of Chriſt, they are not much troubled. That is obſerveable in the <hi>Iews,</hi> though ſenſeleſſe enough under their Idolatry, while they were in outward proſperity, yet being in captivity, how tender are they? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.3, 4. In that Pſalme many things are obſervable to our purpoſe; as firſt, though they were by the pleaſant rivers ſide, yet they could not but mourn for <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> ſake. Again, its obſerved by <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi> as a great teſtimony of their faith and godly zeal, that they carried their harpes with them into ſo ſtrange a land from their own countrey, as their deareſt houſhold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuffe, which they would keep, till God reſtored them to their worſhip in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> again. Further, you may take notice of their refuſall to ſing in a ſtrange land; the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like worſhip of God, and the legall Sacriſices, might not be celebrated in a polluted land. Hereupon, ſee into what an holy paſſion the Church breaks out, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. <hi>If I forget the, O Ieruſalem, let my right hand forget her cunning; If I do not remember thee, let my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth; If I preferre not Ieruſalem above my chief joy:</hi> Here are ſpirituall and heavenly hearts, that can rejoyce more in the reſtitution of the worſhip and ordinances of God, then in all their own private advantages: By this Pſalme you ſee, what an oppreſſion and miſery is upon thoſe, who groan under Church-pollutions. Now one of the main burdens that hath borne down the backs of the godly Miniſters in this kingdome, hath been the want of holy and powerfull diſcipline; <hi>England</hi> was a good ſchool,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113169:9"/>wherein truths were taught, but there wanted a rod to correct vice; the want of this is a grievous burden. Its a paſſage of <hi>Calvins</hi> to <hi>Farell,</hi> ſpeaking of the Sacrament to be with them the next Lords day, <hi>Cogita</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quantis anguſtijs conſtringer, utinam me abſente poſset cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brari, hâc conditione, ut ad vos uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vel manibus reptarem.</hi> What is the cauſe then, that men may be earneſt for the one, and not for the other?</p>
               <p n="1">1. The ſtate reformation agreeth moſt with our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible good; hence we ſhall ſee the <hi>Romanes</hi> and other Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, have adventured themſelves for the Common wealth, and have gloried in being the aſſertors of its li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties; but to promote Chriſts waies, that is contrary to our corrupt hearts: therefore men may be forward to have monopolies and taxes removed, that yet cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to have the ſanctification of the Sabbath, the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ſoul ſaving preaching of Gods Word eſtabliſhed. How few are like <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> of whom <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, <hi>Dilexi virum, qui cum corpore ſolveretur, magis de statu Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiarum, quàm de proprijs periculis angebatur;</hi> he was more carefull about the Church then his own affairs.</p>
               <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Multi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>nt qui d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſciplinam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perium eſſe judica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t ac ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>m ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gationem ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biae aſſignant; quum non fit imperium, aiſi ubi aliqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berur i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>um; ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſuperbia, niſi u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i regligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur diſciplina</hi> Aug.</note> Chriſt hath yokes, and Common wealths are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to receive theſe; In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 3. ſee the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the governours of the earth; <hi>Let us break their bonds, and caſt their cords from us:</hi> The orders of Chriſt are ſo holy, ſo heavenly, ſo ſelf-denying, that few ſtates will ariſe to the obedience of them: And this made the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens object, though very falſely; that Common wealths and the Chriſtian religion cannot ſtand together: And this made ſome prophane men profeſſe, when the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation began in <hi>Lathers</hi> time; that they had rather live under the government of the <hi>Turke,</hi> then where all things ſhould be ordered according to Gods Word; but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113169:9"/>this is to be ignorant of the great happineſſe, both ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and temporall, which the waies of Chriſt bring to a people.</p>
               <p>Beſides the former, there are alſo extrinſecall cauſes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. God leaveth them to their own carnall wiſedome; this is a great judgement of God, when they are left, in matters of Religion, to their own hearts, as in <hi>Jeroboam</hi> and others: ſome have ſaid, the head of every ſacrifice was to be thrown away, and not offered, to ſignifie, that our own carnall apprehenſions muſt be laid aſide in the worſhip of God: Now the Church of God ſcarce ever had a reformation, wherein men have not been in part left to this, as appeareth by that frequent paſſage; <hi>Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the high places were not taken away:</hi> therefore to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, is Gods great worke upon the hearts of men, as he poured his Spirit upon <hi>Zerubbabel;</hi> and take the beſt reformers, while they have no more then man in them, they are like <hi>Sampſon</hi> without his hair, fearfull, worldly, ſelf-ſeeking as others.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The people are unwilling and unprepared: thus it was in <hi>Joſiahs</hi> time, inſomuch that one would wonder to read the ſtory in <hi>Joſiahs</hi> time, to ſee what a generall compliance there was in the whole kingdome with his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, yea, an univerſall ſubmiſſion thereunto; and to obſerve the prophecy of <hi>Zachary,</hi> which is ſaid to be at the ſame time; for in this latter, God by the Prophet. complaineth of them as a very wicked people, yet they gave way to the reformation by <hi>Joſiah;</hi> only this did not laſt, for <hi>Joſiah</hi> is immediately killed, and all the people fall back to their falſe worſhip again, ſo that the inward rottenneſſe and hypocriſie of their hearts, do either ſtop a reformation, intended by governours; or elſe throweth down immediately whatſoever is built up.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:113169:10"/>
               <p n="3">3. A corrupt Miniſtery doth alwaies oppoſe this; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates have not been alwaies able to reforme as they would, becauſe of the wickedneſſe of the Miniſtery, who ſhould indeed have laid the firſt ſtones of every ſpirituall building; Thus Chriſt, whom the zeal of Gods houſe did conſume, by whom was he contradicted in a moſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent manner, but by the Prieſts and Phariſees? Thus <hi>Luther</hi> profeſſed hee found more enemies in the Cloiſters and Monaſteries, then out of wicked and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane places; And is not this to be found in <hi>England?</hi> had not corrupt Miniſters, brokers for Popery, like the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> thrown earth into all our ſprings that we were to drinke of? yet do they repent and humble themſelves for all their ſuperſtitious pollutions to this very day? or are they not rather obſtinate and hardened in the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of them? So then its no wonder, if the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours of a Common wealth do not ſo willingly and fully reforme, when great learned ſcholars, and men much admired for their knowledge ſhall oppoſe it.</p>
               <p>It was a witty ſpeech of <hi>Luthers, Monachica theologia nihil videt in Scriptur is niſi cucullos;</hi> and its true ſtill, great ſcholars corrupted in their judgements, ſee nothing in the Scripture, but what they thinke maketh for Altars, and Ceremonies, and ſuch vanity.</p>
               <div type="application">
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                     </label> This is a reproofe to thoſe who are willing for the one, but cannot abide the other: By what hath been deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you may ſee how happy and bleſſed a thing it is to a Common wealth, when governours and people are as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to have the liberties which Chriſt hath given his Church confirmed, as their ſtate liberties; when they deſire to ſee the Church of God in her ſpirituall beauty, as well as the Common wealth in flouriſhing proſperity. But this is the great eye-ſore and trouble to many; they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113169:10"/>would have it better with the ſtate, and are not affected with a reformation in the Church; and this carnall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition was of old; <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks much to this purpoſe about the Heathens, who cried out of the Chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as the cauſe of all their troubles and miſeries; They would have peace againe, though they had thereby, <hi>mala ſaevis pejora hoſtibus;</hi> and he bringeth in an Heathen, ſaying, Let us have our feaſts again, our merry meetings, <hi>reges non curent quam bonis, ſed quam ſubtitis regnant; non jubeantur dura, non prohibeantur impura;</hi> Let no hard duties be commanded, no impure waies forbidden; <hi>Ille ſit pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licus inimicus cui haec felicitaes diſplicet. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de civit. cap.</hi> 30. I fear theſe things lye in the bottome of many mens hearts, who yet are very willing to have all ſtate grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces taken away.</p>
                  <p>The means to be ſuch Magiſtrates and people, are theſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Be affected with Gods Word, take that for a rule; adore the majeſty and fullneſſe of the Scripture; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not, what this, or that carnall principle ſuggeſteth to you, but ſay, how is it written? and how do we read in the Scripture? The Church of God is tied to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, to fetch all nouriſhment and ſupport from it, as the childe is faſtened by the navell to the mother, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief and maintenance of it: What hath made men here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques in the myſteries of the Trinity and Deity of Chriſt, but only attending to reaſon, and not Scripture? they will have us ſhew the like in the creatures; but the Father ſaid well to the Arian that demanded ſo, <hi>Da mihi alium Deum, &amp; aliam Trinitatem tibi ostendam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Get an heavenly heart and minde, which will prize the ordinances of God; till this be in men, they will not move, or ſtirre in any Temple-worke. Its no marvell if <hi>David</hi> have ſuch a deſire to build an houſe to God, when
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113169:11"/>he cryeth out, <hi>How amiable are thy Tabernacles, O Lord?</hi> Pſal. 84.1. <hi>Bleſſed are they that dwell in thy houſe,</hi> &amp;c. So when he is in baniſhment, what is that which he ſo long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for? is it to have his peace and outward tranquillity again, or not rather to ſee the power and glory of God, as he had ſeen it in the ſanctuary? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.31, 2.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Humble your ſelves for former known pollutions, or for negligence and remiſſeneſſe in reformation, when opportunities have been offered. Who knoweth whether much of this worke that is now to do, might not have been diſpatched heretofore, if the hearts of men in place had been for it? Can we ſay, that it is not the ſinne of Parliaments and governours heretofore, that the Ark is not already ſetled? and how neceſſary our humiliations are for former known defilements and ſuperſtitions, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.10, 11.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Remember theſe conſiderations.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What the thoughts are which God hath about a worſhip that is none of his, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. <hi>You worſhip you know not what;</hi> men do they know not what, howſoever they dote moſt upon their own invented worſhip. There is a Papiſt <hi>Raymundus</hi> ſaith, There are as many myſteries in the Maſſe, as drops in the ſea, Angels in Heaven, Starres in the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, atomes in the Sunne-beames, or ſand in the ſea ſhore; but that which is highly eſteemed among men, is abominable before God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The danger of our own hearts in ſuch things; God doth frequently forbid our own wiſdome and diſcretion, in matters concerning him; and the wiſer men are, the more abſurd they have been in their worſhip, when they have not been guided by the light of the Scripture, as in the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> who were noted to be a fountain of the arts, and much knowledge; they were of all the Heathens
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113169:11"/>moſt ridiculous about their gods. And all Popery may ſufficiently advertiſe us, how dangerous it is to leave Gods word, and to follow our own imaginations: In things of this life, a Magiſtrate <hi>de jure ſuo tantum remittere poteſt, quantum pacis ſtudium requiret: ſed alia eſt ratio ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualis regiminis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The unprofitableneſſe of any ſuch way for a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall benefit; whatſoever doctrine, worſhip or ordinance is not of the Lords inſtitution, can never be bleſt to any ſpirituall effect upon the ſoul: The word of promiſe doth alwaies ſuppoſe a word of inſtitution.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Godly men cannot rejoyce in outward bleſſings; if this be wanting, as you heard before of <hi>David,</hi> though he might have his countrey, his liberty again, yet that was not ſo great a good, as to enjoy God again; it is riches and the Goſpel, peace and the Goſpel that makes a people happy.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. This is a great argument to prevail with God; what an argument is this in prayer; Lord bleſſe theſe Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, this Parliament, for they ſet up thy Kingdome? and conſider that every time you pray that petition in the Lords prayer, that the Kingdome of God would come; the meaning is, that the powerfull preaching of Gods word, and the wholeſome diſpenſation of the ordinances may every where be ſetled.</p>
                  <p>But againſt all theſe Arguments for a Reformation, there are many objections brought; I will inſtance in three only.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Some ſay, this is to make all Religion ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous; what a vanity, and inconſtancy doth this ſeem to be, to have one year, one kinde of ſervice and worſhip of God, and another the next year? Now to this I anſwer theſe things.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:113169:12"/>
                  <p n="1">1. It is indeed a very hard thing to take men off from their religious uſages, though they have no ſolid ground to retain them. Thus <hi>Auſtin</hi> he complained, <hi>Genus eſt morbi graviſsimi, eorum qui dicunt nobis, verè quidem dicitur non est quod reſpondeatur, ſed durum eſt nobis traditione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> parentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> relinquere;</hi> This doth much trouble men to leave cuſtoms, which by long tract of time have made an awfull impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon their conſcience. And thus <hi>Auſtin</hi> at another time, <hi>Senſi ſaepe dolens &amp; gemens,</hi> &amp;c. he often perceived with much grief, that many perturbations and contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were raiſed in many things, one reaſon whereof was, becauſe it was not their cuſtom in their countrey to doe ſo. Therefore this muſt be acknowledged, that people will generally ſtartle and be aſtoniſhed, if an old cuſtome be denied them, though they have no Scripture for it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It may fall out, that it is ſo far from being mutabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that it is a duty to leave off ſuch things as have been practiſed: Thus when the kingdome of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had ſet up many idolatricall practices, was it their ſinne, becauſe they made their change, or not rather their duty? and thus in Popery, when God cauſed the light of Reformation to ſhine out of that thick darkneſſe; was this levity and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tability, becauſe there were no Altars, no Images, no Maſſe, where they were uſed to be for many hundred years? No, God commanded them to leave <hi>Babylon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. There is an alteration eſſentiall and deſtructive, and an alteration accidentall and perfective. Where the Churches of God retain the true Doctrine, there is not an eſſentiall alteration, nor can Religion properly be ſaid to be changed. And thus when calumniatours ſay, that we are ſetting up a new Religion; it's but a ſlander, for the doctrine that hath heretofore been retained in <hi>England</hi> (I ſpeak not of Papizing and Arminianizing perſons) is not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113169:12"/>changed; we ſtill retain the Doctrine of the Scriptures, of the Trinity, of Chriſt, of juſtifying faith: therefore all the alteration is accidentall, concerning rituals and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, which alteration makes to the perfection and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being of the Doctrine, for the Doctrine that is <hi>anima,</hi> and Diſcipline that is the nerves whereby the body is compact together.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. No Reformers that ever God raiſed up in the Church would own themſelves ſo far perfect, as that there needed no addition; we ſhould doe wrong to the bleſſed Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, if ſo be that we ſhould think they themſelves thought they had attained to ſuch a Reformation, as needed no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Reformation. It's expreſſed in the Common-prayer book, That till the primitive Diſcipline may be reſtored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, they ordered for the preſent thus, and thus. Nay cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly were the godly Martyrs commanded to come out of their graves, and to ſee what is now doing in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> they would exceedingly rejoyce to ſee the fruit of their prayers.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. It lieth as a dutie upon Churches to improve their talents, as well as particular perſons.</p>
                  <p>If perſons are to grow in knowledge and Reformation, then why not Churches? not as if that Academicall prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of the <hi>Socinians</hi> were to be received, that it is lawfull every moneth to alter our opinions in the Doctrine of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; that is to bring in Atheiſme at laſt: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding there is to be a growth in the clearer knowledge even of eſſentials; as when a childe groweth, he doth not get new members or parts: only they grow in their kinde: It is <hi>profectus,</hi> not <hi>alteratio,</hi> as <hi>Lyrinenſis</hi> called it; and as for thoſe things that are not abſolutely eſſentiall; we ſee by experience what need there is, that Churches ſhould daily encreaſe in their knowledge. And ſo much for this Objection.</p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:113169:13"/>
                  <p>The next Objection is of thoſe, who ſay, It's no ſuch dangerous thing to live and die in errours, therefore there needeth not ſo much ſtrictneſſe and accurateneſſe herein, and the handling of this is neceſſary in theſe times, when it is thought that hereſie is but a theologicall fiction, and that it is great innocency. Now though great care ought to be uſed, for the declining of all tyranny in Diſcipline againſt errours; and in opinions of leſſe concernment, a Magiſtrate is not to make the <hi>major</hi> propoſition; a jailor, the <hi>minor,</hi> and a priſon the concluſion; yet that people may be more afraid &amp; tremble about errour then they do. It is good to confider, firſt, a man may pervert Scripture to his own damnation by errour, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Which the unlearned and unſtable wreſt to their own damnation:</hi> So that a man may damn himſelf by errours, as well as by a wicked life. Yea <hi>Oecumenius</hi> makes it as great a ſinne to wreſt and mangle the Scripture, as to take the bodies of the holy Pen-men, and to murder them; conſider that place, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.6. <hi>Adde thou not to his words, leſt he reprove thee.</hi> By reproving, is meant a reall chaſtiſement and affliction; now when thou lieſt under heavie troubles, thou enquireſt, what ſin have I done? What iniquity is it that I have committed, for which God doth thus heavily afflict me? never conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it may be for a ſinfull and carnall opinion. If therefore errour may be the poiſon, and damnation of a mans ſoule, it is not to be judged, as a thing of pardon, rather then of blame, as ſome would have it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Hereſies and errours come from damnable cauſes; therefore they are not to be ſleighted: the generall cauſe of them is made to be the fleſh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.20. and reckoned in the nature of them with groſſe ſins, <hi>murders, whoredoms,</hi> &amp;c. and joyned in the damnable effect of them, <hi>They that do
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113169:13"/>theſe things ſhall never inherit the Kingdom of heaven;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any neceſſity of that forced interpretation, to take hereſies (there ſpoken of) for contentions and ſtrifes, ſeeing though the word may denote ſome wilfull pertina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, yet it frequently ſignifieth ſome pertinacy about re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious matters; by this therefore it appeareth, that a man may be carnall by his head-ſins, as well as by his hand-ſinnes; then there are more particular cauſes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by Scripture of errour, which are damnable, as obſtinacy, covetouſneſſe, pride, and vain-glory, as in <hi>Marcion,</hi> when he ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, he would throw the fire-bals of contention, which ſhould be unquenchable like thoſe of hell: eſpecially theſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours are of a damnable cauſe, when they come from a looſeneſſe of heart, as thoſe that diſpute againſt the mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Sabbath, and the ſtrict keeping of it, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the obligation of the morall law, and the divinity of the Scriptures; therefore goe to the fountain of every errour, and ſee how dangerous that is.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The ſeverall acts, or nature, wherein it conſiſteth, is damnable. There is a learned man, that confidently maintaineth the word Hereſie is never uſed in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture in a middle or indifferent ſenſe, but alwaies in an ill notion: I ſhall not call that into queſtion now; only we ſay, as it is taken eccleſiaſtically, the acts of it are very hainous, as that it's putting a lie upon the holy Ghoſt: if the ſalfe prophets were ſo threatned for ſaying, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> when the Lord did not ſay ſo; then muſt the like condemnation fall upon them, who ſay, <hi>Thus ſaith the Scripture,</hi> when it ſaith it not. Again, Gods Word is the publike Standard; it's the teſtament of Chriſt: now how harnous a thing is it judged to falſifie the laſt will of a man? Again, Gods Word is precious and dear
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113169:14"/>to him, and he will hear the words and the groans, as it were, which this corrupt heart makes in it.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The conſequents of it are damnable, for errour is like the plague and infection, which deſtroyeth many others. <hi>Arius una ſcintilla fuit;</hi> and yet how did it fire the whole world? and how well were it, if <hi>Luthers</hi> temptation were upon many men, <hi>Tune ſolus ſapis?</hi> art thou only wiſe? what if thou be damned, and draweſt many thouſands to hell with thee? therefore it is a true ſaying, <hi>Quicquid in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionem divinam committitur, in omnium fit injuriam.</hi> Again, theſe ſins of errours pollute the minde and underſtanding, which are the choiſeſt parts of man: alwaies the ſins that are <hi>majoris infamiae,</hi> greater reproach among men, are not preſently <hi>majoris reatus,</hi> of the greater guilt before God. Is not the devil called an unclean ſpirit? yet he hath no bodily wickedneſſe, therefore doctrine being the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of practice it is dangerous to erre there. And then laſtly, ſuch ſins we are hardly convinced of. An out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward groſſe ſin naturall conſcience may condemn, but it cannot doe ſo in matters of faith, becauſe they are ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturally revealed. Theſe things duly conſidered, may make men pray, and again, pray that God would not leave them to their own underſtandings.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, There is no ſolid excuſe, or plea can be made for it. Not that it is a mans ignorance, and therefore we are to do with them as blinde men, whom we pity, and not beat, for by this means the Jews who oppoſed Chriſt ſhould have been excuſed; and thoſe who thought they did God good ſervice in killing of the Prophets: inſomuch that a man may be under much guilt by errour; and yet be perſwaded he is in the right way; neither doth this excuſe him, that he cannot help it, or remove his errour no more then he can remove a mountain into the ſea, for then this
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113169:14"/>would excuſe thoſe alſo who are captivated to any ſinfull way; and certainly the commands of God are as much to underſtand the truth, and to believe what God hath reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as to embrace in our will and affections what is good; neither doth this excuſe them, that they have good inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ends, for the <hi>Socinians</hi> profeſſe they dare not hold Chriſt to be the true God, equall with the Father, out of reverence and reſpect to the Father, leſt they ſhould diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him. Nor laſtly, that every man is fallible, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no man may judge another to erre, for if becauſe all may erre, it would follow that they do erre, then all truths in Religion would be quite overthrown.</p>
                  <p>The laſt Objection is, wherein ſhould <hi>England</hi> be reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Hath not the Church thereof been famous for her or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxy? what can be done more to her? I anſwer, to ſettle wholſome orders, and ſpirituall diſcipline againſt ſin. It's not enough for a Church to be orthodox, but ſhe ought to be holy alſo, and the Scripture is not only a rule for faith, but for our life alſo: now take thoſe places of Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. 2 <hi>Theſs.</hi> 3.6. what little influence had they up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Kingdom? O, but this will bring men into bondage and ſlavery! no more then to have Phyſicians in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, then to have Pilates in a ſhip: theſe orders of Chriſt are meerly medicinall, <hi>utiliter vincitur, cui licentia iniquitatis eripitur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, theſe orders of Chriſt are not terrible, for he hath commanded them to be adminiſtred, with all love, tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and compaſſion. <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, while he was ſtill leaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Popiſh principles of contrition, and their penance, there was no more bitter word in all the Scripture then <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipiſce,</hi> repent: but when he underſtood the Goſpel, then it was precious and welcome. Thus it may be with the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Chriſt, while they are lookt upon as made odious
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113169:15"/>by the calumnies of men, they are ready to reject them; but if once underſtood according to the inſtitution, uſe and end of them, then with <hi>Moſes,</hi> you may take this Serpent that you were afraid of, and it will become a rod.</p>
                  <p>Further conſider, that it's no bondage to take Chriſts yoke: but to be under the command of ſin, that is a ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. To be <hi>ſervum tot Dominorum, quot vitiorum;</hi> this is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a great vaſſalage.</p>
                  <p>Again, For want of ſpirituall order and government in a Church, many ſins goe unreformed, which yet do much diſhonour God; for commonly States, in making of laws, conſider a ſin, as it is deſtructive to the Common-wealth, and as injurious to others, and doe not for the moſt part at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to a ſin, as it is offenſive to God: now what a ſad thing is it to conſider that the ſea is not fuller of water, or the air of flies, then towns and cities are full of wretched oaths, and blaſphemous curfings, which certainly do much provoke God againſt us, whereas ſpirituall order would be a ſpeciall means to remove theſe.</p>
                  <p>And laſtly, lay to heart ſeriouſly how far Popery hath prevailed with Kingdoms and States, to debaſe and wrong themſelves indeed, in their outward liberties, to ſet up that; and ſhall not Chriſt prevail to have his doctrine and orders ſetled, which will indeed be no detriment, but a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of all honour and dignity?</p>
                  <p>And thus have I anſwered the three main Objections.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>I come to the ſecond Doctrine, which is,</p>
               <p>That the work of Reformation, requireth the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and conflux of many noble and excellent graces. It's like the choice compound of ointment, which <hi>Aaron</hi> was to make. As</p>
               <p>Firſt, A clear underſtanding of Gods will out of his Word. Thus the King he was to write Gods Word, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113169:15"/>to be acquainted familiarly with it, that ſo he might be the more able to reform all abuſes that may creep into the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God: it's a great fault, when men in place and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er think that matters of Religion doe not at all belong to them; whereas they cannot diſcharge their duties, if they know not by the Word what to doe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Zeal for Gods glory, and his pure worſhip. Such as was in <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and moſt remarkably in Chriſt himſelf. It's an excellent thing, when Magiſtrates lay to heart Gods diſhonour more then their own, and are more ſollicitous that the laws of Chriſt may be beſt, then their own laws. It was an ingenuous way of reproving, which one orthodox Biſhop uſed to an <hi>Arian</hi> Emperour, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called into the Emperours preſence, where his ſon alſo was, the Biſhop made his low obeyſance to the Emperour, but took no notice at all of the Emperours ſon; at which there was great offence taken; but the Biſhop replied, that if he would not honour the Son of God, why ſhould he regard his ſon: So why ſhould we look upon it as an hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous thing, when men will not keep our Laws, if we doe not Gods?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Publike affections, and love to the ſoul of others. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe a man beclothed with a publike ſpirit, he cannot la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for a Reformation. <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> though it was well with him, yet how deeply and ſadly is he affected, becauſe the Temple lieth deſolate? and thus Chriſt himſelf at that very time, when he was received with the greateſt accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, he doth not minde them, but <hi>weeps for Jeruſalem.</hi> Then hath God dealt graciouſly with your hearts, when neither riches, honours, or any perſonall dignity can do you any good, till <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> be ſetled a praiſe in the earth, as it was with <hi>David.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Sincerity and pure aims. For though Governours
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113169:16"/>may be carried far in a Reformation, yet if pure love to God and his Ordinances be not the Star which leadeth them, the iſſue will be very uncomfortable; you have a ſad inſtance in <hi>Iehu,</hi> who though he did all according to Gods heart (as the Scripture ſaith) yet <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1. God threatens to be avenged on him. Take heed therefore of corrupt, politicall deſigns in promoting Gods work. <hi>Nazianzen</hi> complained of ſome that were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: This hath made God many times let his own Ark fall into the hands of the Philiſtims, not but that his cauſe was dear to him, only thoſe who managed it, had ſelfiſh and particular intereſts.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Humility under all the honours God puts upon them. This was wonderfull in <hi>Gideon</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> whereas men, who are lifted up by any ſucceſſe that God beſtoweth on them, are like a blazing ſtar, that make a great luſtre at firſt, but at laſt end in ſlime. <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt that wrought a great Reformation, and the eyes of the world was upon him, yet he rejoyceth, becauſe he muſt decreaſe, and Chriſt increaſe.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Exemplary holines of life. This obligation cometh upon all Reformers, by that generall rule, He which repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth others, ought himſelf to be free from thoſe ſins. The examples of Reformers, they are to others, as the partico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured ſticks to <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſheep: and indeed how uncomely is it, when Governours make laws againſt impiety, prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sabbath, contempt of holineſſe; and ſuch ſins be found in their lives, or in their families? Now this is a great part of Reformation, when the lives and families of men are changed, as well as when Reformation is in the publike worſhip and Ordinances.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Fortitude and courage, accompanied with faith. For all Reformations meet with much oppoſition and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. When <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſent meſſengers up and down for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113169:16"/>the pure keeping of the Paſſeover, they were mocked and ſcorned. Now to goe thorow all the accuſations and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies of men, yea and many exerciſes from God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, this requireth, as humility and patience to be under them, ſo faith and courage, to be above them.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Prudence and ſingular wiſdom. This fact of <hi>Gideon,</hi> going with ſome few men in the night, is queſtioned by ſome as a weakneſſe in him, whereas indeed it was his great prudence. Any that hath read eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories may obſerve that the imprudence of men, hath much hindred the propagation of truth; only there muſt be care that pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence doe not degenerate into carnall and meer State-wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; God hath made ſuch wiſdom in the end great folly, eſpecially when it is accompanied with the corruption of his worſhip.</p>
               <div type="application">
                  <p>The Uſe is for Exhortation, to be filled with all theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent qualifications, God hath put an opportunity into our hands, and we have all covenanted according to our places and callings to ſet upon this work. Let us therfore be humbled and aſhamed this day, that we have with no more zeal promoted it. How have Governours, and others, who have not had ſuch advantages, ſuch intereſts in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, done much for Chriſt and his Ordinances? and do theſe things ſpeedily, leſt hereaſter you may in the anguiſh and grief of your ſpirits call for the time and opportunities again, but cannot obtain them; let not the generation to come ſay, our Governours indeed delivered a Common wealth from thraldome, but beſet the faithfull Miniſters, and the godly people of the land, under as many groans and troubles as ever before.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
